<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Lend Me Your Ears</title>
    <description>Welcome to Lend Me Your Ears, a blog by John Kageche</description>
    <link>http://lendmeyourears.co.ke/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://lendmeyourears.co.ke/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2015 16:55:01 +0300</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 May 2015 16:55:01 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to sell to different segments in the organisation</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;It is the consummate seller who is able to resist the urge to volunteer (unnecessary) details of what the product can do.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A business to business sale many times requires the presentation to be done across different cadre before it is consummated. Few sellers do this. Many, for lack of trying; others for lack of knowledge.  To succeed in adapting one’s presentation to the commensurate segment, here’s what research shows each segment is often interested in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Management&lt;/h2&gt;
The bottom line; solutions, not problems, and reducing costs. With this in mind, it becomes particularly important for the seller, say of the IT solution, to demonstrate its value, impact on the business and the expected outcome.  All in a short span.&lt;i&gt;“Your staff in IT confirms that the Robot program is easily compatible with your system. With this solution, you will increase your operational efficiency by 45% with surprisingly minimal to nil increase to your costs. Based on your historical performance, and borrowing from anticipated projections you will easily double your profits this year at the minimum because of Robot.”&lt;/i&gt;  It is the consummate seller who is able to resist the urge to volunteer (unnecessary) details of  what the product can do, what it can do, what it can…you catch my drift. Usually, this is done in the hope that the senior officer will be wowed. Many times, he shifts attention to his phone or emails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Specialists&lt;/h2&gt;
The joke goes that a specialist is someone who knows too much about very little and continues to know more and more about less and less until eventually he knows about almost nothing. Specialists tend to focus on their areas of expertise and have blinders to everything else. (Salespeople are especially notorious at this) For this reason, the IT seller will focus on how Robot will ease or benefit the specialist’s area of expertise and nothing else.  Specialists include chefs, webmasters, software engineers etc, and they want to know how their expertise influences the organization and where their expertise is not being utilized &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Professionals&lt;/h2&gt;
The one thing that permeates all professionals (excepting politicians assuming they are) is doing the right thing which usually translates to following procedure. Not yours but theirs. Not necessarily how your product works but if it flouts any procedure or policy. The seller who shows how Robot will impact the organizational policy and how procedure will be followed will more likely connect with the professional than the one who doesn’t. Examples of professionals include human resource and public relations executives and accountants. Ethics and morals are usually high on their agenda. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Lay employees &lt;/h2&gt;
I’m reminded of the messenger (call him Juma) who was the shop steward at an organization I used to be with. This one year we did not get bonuses owing to poor performance. We had been on bonuses consistently for 6 years so Juma refused to understand why this year was different. I’ll never forget what he asked the MD, while in defense of the union. &lt;i&gt;&quot;Did I not deliver all letters in time? Was there a driver who failed in his duty? Is there any work that we did not do? We did what we were required to do, so if the company didn’t make profits, that’s not my doing.&quot;&lt;/i&gt; Believe it or not, they got their bonuses! Lay employees (clerical staff, waiters, drivers) are focused on pay and working conditions. Showing how Robot will impact on this stands a greater chance of it being taken up faster&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless asked to do otherwise, focus only the area of interest; and to thrive, do this at preparation stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    /* * * CONFIGURATION VARIABLES * * */
    var disqus_shortname = 'lendmeyourears';
    var disqus_identifier = '2015-05-11';
    
    /* * * DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE * * */
    (function() {
        var dsq = document.createElement('script'); dsq.type = 'text/javascript'; dsq.async = true;
        dsq.src = '//' + disqus_shortname + '.disqus.com/embed.js';
        (document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0] || document.getElementsByTagName('body')[0]).appendChild(dsq);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;!--
//&lt;![CDATA[
	twatchData = 'page='+encodeURIComponent( window.location );
	if( typeof document.referrer != 'undefined' &amp;&amp; document.referrer != '' ) {
		twatchData += '&amp;ref='+encodeURIComponent( document.referrer );
	}
	twatchData += '&amp;no_cookies=true';
	if( typeof screen.width != 'undefined' ) {
		twatchData += '&amp;resolution='+screen.width+'x'+screen.height;
	}
	document.write('&lt;scr'+'ipt type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; '+
	'src=&quot;http://www.lendmeyourears.co.ke/twatch/remote/js_logger.php?'+twatchData+'&quot;&gt;'+
	'&lt;/scr'+'ipt&gt;');
//]]&gt;
//--&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2015 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://lendmeyourears.co.ke/2015/05/11/have-the-right/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lendmeyourears.co.ke/2015/05/11/have-the-right/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How sellers in charitable organizations can quickly embrace a commercial outlook</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;While hitherto fully-fledged charitable organizations strive to embrace a quasi-commercial outlook, it is imperative for their salespeople to morph at a faster rate.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the dire credit crunch happened in the West a few years back, many charitable organizations were forced to interrogate how they do business. Before, donor money would flow, and all the recipient charitable organizations had to do was initiate, oversee and submit progress reports on programs run. The credit crunch dried several such taps and now these organizations are finding themselves in need of a more pro-active way of raising funds. In fact, some have diversified their product offering (products they offer) and recruited sales people (though most do not call them this) to seek said funds from commercial corporations. Caught between charity and commerce, these institutions are struggling to rhyme the strategy, systems and structures of a charitable organization with those of a commercial entity. How then does one sell in these institutions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;1. Accept your status&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term salesperson may not be on your card but approaching your job as such will immensely increase your chances of success. Ones' attitude has- and will always- play a key role in their selling success.  The attitude that, &lt;i&gt;“I’m special and not like those salespeople”&lt;/i&gt; will work against you. Immerse yourself in the new experience, absorb all you can and generally make it easy to shorten your learning curve. Don’t work against yourself.  Choose the salesperson you admire and emulate him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;2. Avoid charitable thinking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, steer clear of expecting a sale based on &lt;i&gt;“we are raising funds to fight poverty”&lt;/i&gt;. This is usually driven by the notion that the organization will be emotionally moved to act. It’s not moved, and it doesn’t act. And before you condemn them for being heartless commercial entities, how often (if ever) do you give money to beggars or the poor? How regularly (if ever) do you tithe? I’m willing to bet, closer to zero than always. In addition, these very organizations already have corporate social responsibility programs and some outright foundations, both which put you in direct competition. Also, the country has been fighting illiteracy, poverty and sickness since independence and now 50 years later you come along professing to have the magic bullet? The seller must remain alert to these realities of 'commercial' thinking which were hitherto absent in 'charitable' thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;3. Make business sense&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, as the seller, your 'fighting poverty' does not exempt you from demonstrating to the corporate world why it makes business sense to partner with you through funding a program or releasing staff to go act as mentors in, say, a village polytechnic. And the key here is business sense. Commercial entities are driven first by the business sense of the idea, followed by what’s in it for our staff and lastly, the social aspect of “helping”. This sequence of thinking must be paramount in the seller's mind if he is to succeed. So, when selling to a large motor vehicle dealer as to why they should release their staff, even for a day, the dealer will more likely be moved by the business sense of touching base with what the young mechanics-to-be are taught about repairing the dealer’s vehicles, than he will be with, &lt;i&gt;“you will motivate your staff”&lt;/i&gt; or worse, &lt;i&gt;“you will be socially responsible”&lt;/i&gt;. From the buyer’s perspective, he will be &lt;i&gt;irresponsible&lt;/i&gt; if he releases staff for a day on a venture that does not make business sense!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    /* * * CONFIGURATION VARIABLES * * */
    var disqus_shortname = 'lendmeyourears';
    var disqus_identifier = '2015-05-05';
    
    /* * * DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE * * */
    (function() {
        var dsq = document.createElement('script'); dsq.type = 'text/javascript'; dsq.async = true;
        dsq.src = '//' + disqus_shortname + '.disqus.com/embed.js';
        (document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0] || document.getElementsByTagName('body')[0]).appendChild(dsq);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;!--
//&lt;![CDATA[
	twatchData = 'page='+encodeURIComponent( window.location );
	if( typeof document.referrer != 'undefined' &amp;&amp; document.referrer != '' ) {
		twatchData += '&amp;ref='+encodeURIComponent( document.referrer );
	}
	twatchData += '&amp;no_cookies=true';
	if( typeof screen.width != 'undefined' ) {
		twatchData += '&amp;resolution='+screen.width+'x'+screen.height;
	}
	document.write('&lt;scr'+'ipt type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; '+
	'src=&quot;http://www.lendmeyourears.co.ke/twatch/remote/js_logger.php?'+twatchData+'&quot;&gt;'+
	'&lt;/scr'+'ipt&gt;');
//]]&gt;
//--&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2015 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://lendmeyourears.co.ke/2015/05/05/how-sellers-in/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lendmeyourears.co.ke/2015/05/05/how-sellers-in/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Debt collection is in itself a formidable salesman</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;To thrive, sellers must take debt collection in stride.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the ultimate objective of sales is to generate income, then debt collection is in itself a salesman. A reader friend of mine told me of an interesting experience he had a few years back. When he joined this firm that sold tires, they were at a deficit position of a whopping 420 million shillings. As Sales General Manager, he gave an unusual instruction to the sales team: &lt;i&gt;“forget new business; collect”&lt;/i&gt;. That was the brief. Go ye forth and collect. And collect they did; so successfully that by the end of that year, they were in a credit position of 20 million shillings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regrettably, many salespeople dread to collect. They see it as the fly in the relationship ointment. For instance, if I’m selling organic pest solutions to flower farms, I’ll be happy to do the demo which lasts a season (three months), and also excitedly see to it that the buyer gets his goods delivered; but because I don’t want to ‘spoil’ the cozy relationship I’ve built with this buyer, I want someone else (read Finance) to ask for the money. Sometimes finance does, but bereft of a brief about the relationship dynamics involved, friction is generated and the relationship marred. Usually though, finance doesn’t, and instead follows policy and suspends or closes the account when the next supply is requested and the past one hadn’t been paid for or the cheque bounced. Unbelievably, the seller, drunk in the aroma of the utopic relationship, gets offended arguing, &lt;i&gt;“But we will lose the customer.”&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basic selling reminds us that the sale is complete when payment has occurred. Progressive sellers know that even when the structure allows (as it does in business-to-business selling) for someone else to collect, this only transfers responsibility- not accountability- for the sale. And why? Because, the same basics tell us that growth is most optimally achieved through existing customers themselves and those they refer. Having a pulse on the relationship, irrespective of who is handling the account at the time, therefore becomes a necessity for the seller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, it is only human to want to pay later (or never) so long as a loophole exists. Its why 'pay yourself first' is a cardinal rule to financial success. How successful would the government be if they allowed us to pay our taxes when we wanted to? Sellers dreading to upset the apple cart by collecting payments overdue, only serve to create that loophole that buyers exploit leading to such deficits to the tune of Ksh. 420m. He does this by building relationships (selling) inside just as he does outside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This aside, an overdue debt still works against that sale because a debtor is less likely to order from you if he has your debt. &lt;i&gt;'Let me pay it first'&lt;/i&gt;, he will say. In the meantime, he will most likely be getting his supply on credit or cash elsewhere. After all, his business won’t stall because he has your debt. Yet, you are letting yours stall because of the same reason. Movement of money in and out of a firm is the lifeblood of a business and critical to success; this is also true for you- the individual. Your very tools of trade (salaries included) depend on this. On the other hand, if he has paid up, he is very likely to exploit the opportunity and state, &lt;i&gt;“Hebu, supply me with tyres, now that I don’t have your debt!”&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    /* * * CONFIGURATION VARIABLES * * */
    var disqus_shortname = 'lendmeyourears';
    var disqus_identifier = '2015-04-27';
    
    /* * * DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE * * */
    (function() {
        var dsq = document.createElement('script'); dsq.type = 'text/javascript'; dsq.async = true;
        dsq.src = '//' + disqus_shortname + '.disqus.com/embed.js';
        (document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0] || document.getElementsByTagName('body')[0]).appendChild(dsq);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;!--
//&lt;![CDATA[
	twatchData = 'page='+encodeURIComponent( window.location );
	if( typeof document.referrer != 'undefined' &amp;&amp; document.referrer != '' ) {
		twatchData += '&amp;ref='+encodeURIComponent( document.referrer );
	}
	twatchData += '&amp;no_cookies=true';
	if( typeof screen.width != 'undefined' ) {
		twatchData += '&amp;resolution='+screen.width+'x'+screen.height;
	}
	document.write('&lt;scr'+'ipt type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; '+
	'src=&quot;http://www.lendmeyourears.co.ke/twatch/remote/js_logger.php?'+twatchData+'&quot;&gt;'+
	'&lt;/scr'+'ipt&gt;');
//]]&gt;
//--&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://lendmeyourears.co.ke/2015/04/27/debt-collection-is/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lendmeyourears.co.ke/2015/04/27/debt-collection-is/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Asking 'So?' will let you look outwards to the buyer and the sale, not inwards to you</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;How do you get to speak in the language that connects with the buyer? By asking, “So?”. Virtually all in-house sales trainings busy themselves with product knowledge. So if I’m selling waste-water treatment equipment, my in-house training will focus on the types of plants we have, their specifications, what they can do and how they do it. So carbon filters, insulated transfer chamber, pit walls and other technical terms will litter the training. In-house sales trainings look inwards- this is who we are; this is what we do; this is how we do it. All good, to a point. The point at which a chairman of a multinational manufacturing concern once told his global staff, &lt;i&gt;“the customer does not buy strategy- if our seasoning is not on the shelf when she wants it and if it fails to spice her food as she wants it to, then be damned with us and our lofty strategies!”&lt;/i&gt; In-house sessions look inwards, yet successful selling looks outwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is for this reason that upon release to the field, ostensibly equipped to sell, many sales people quickly hit a wall. Much like the theory of driving school is as different as death is from sleep, when compared to the practice evidenced when the novice hits the road. When addressing the engineer, ozone injector, oil skimmer unit and sludge output may keep the conversation going but is highly unlikely to get the sale going for two reasons: facts alone never sold, emotions do; also, besides the engineer, the others who most likely comprise the decision-making unit won’t understand half what you are saying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How then does the seller connect his product to the buyer's need? Through the use of the one word question, “So?”. It’s considered rude, yet in selling, is indispensable if we are to succeed. It is not meant to be verbalized, but silently shouting it will force you to find points of convergence between the buyer’s need and your product’s solution- if at all any exist. And why, “So?” because, that’s exactly what the buyer is asking himself when you rattle on about how you have been doing this for the past seven years (So?), this establishment and that establishment has it (So?) and how the center-withdrawal coriolus pipe is unique to your plant…So?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;So, based on the water requirements in your 100 apartments and borrowing from our experience over the past seven years and similar establishments we have worked with, on average you will require 10,000 litres of water readily available at any one time if your guests are to enjoy their stay. Because water sanitation, reliability and conservation are important to you and us, continual research over our seven years has seen us improve our recycling technology so that now you will use a whopping 80% less water and you can put the cost savings into phase two of your ongoing construction.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether in in-house training or the field, go through every aspect of your product and put each to the “So?” test. And don’t stop at, for instance, 'it will save you money': that’s still abstract. Stretch it further. So? So, you will incur less interest at the bank or so your customer will be happier with you when you transfer the unexpected cost savings to them or, so, (whatever it is you know will benefit him)…So?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    /* * * CONFIGURATION VARIABLES * * */
    var disqus_shortname = 'lendmeyourears';
    var disqus_identifier = '2015-04-20';
    
    /* * * DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE * * */
    (function() {
        var dsq = document.createElement('script'); dsq.type = 'text/javascript'; dsq.async = true;
        dsq.src = '//' + disqus_shortname + '.disqus.com/embed.js';
        (document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0] || document.getElementsByTagName('body')[0]).appendChild(dsq);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;!--
//&lt;![CDATA[
	twatchData = 'page='+encodeURIComponent( window.location );
	if( typeof document.referrer != 'undefined' &amp;&amp; document.referrer != '' ) {
		twatchData += '&amp;ref='+encodeURIComponent( document.referrer );
	}
	twatchData += '&amp;no_cookies=true';
	if( typeof screen.width != 'undefined' ) {
		twatchData += '&amp;resolution='+screen.width+'x'+screen.height;
	}
	document.write('&lt;scr'+'ipt type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; '+
	'src=&quot;http://www.lendmeyourears.co.ke/twatch/remote/js_logger.php?'+twatchData+'&quot;&gt;'+
	'&lt;/scr'+'ipt&gt;');
//]]&gt;
//--&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://lendmeyourears.co.ke/2015/04/20/asking-so-will/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lendmeyourears.co.ke/2015/04/20/asking-so-will/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Learn how to easily close the sale from daily experiences</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;En-route home, you see a pair of shoes being sold on the street. You want the shoe. The seller sees that and says, &lt;i&gt;“Karibu siste. Kujaribu ni bure” (Welcome, my sister. It’s free to try on).&lt;/i&gt; You do. He tells you it goes well with your dressing. You know this but the assurance is still welcome and your excitement at hearing this shows in your face. &lt;i&gt;&quot;Hiyo kiatu ni ya mguu yako madam.&quot; (That shoe fits you perfectly madam).&lt;/i&gt; And with this he proceeds to gather and wrap your “old” pair in a plastic bag, and while giving the package to you says, &lt;i&gt;“Nipe mia tatu tu” (Give me three hundred shillings only).&lt;/i&gt; And you find yourself reaching for the purse and giving him the money. Several closes have just happened. A minor close (try it on), a test close (you do), a custom-fit close (the shoe was created for your foot) and the ultimate one, the assumptive close (wrapping the old pair without asking you if you are buying but instead assuming that you will; and you do).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the corporate world, you have a contract you need signed. It could be account opening, tenancy agreement or purchase of an elevator. Everything before this stage of signing pans out and the client is happy. Being human however, he hesitates. You say, &lt;i&gt;“Let’s go over the main points together. Is this ok?” (minor close). We will ship in the elevator in six weeks and install it on the fourteenth week of the project which will be two weeks after it gets here. Is this correct? (Test close). The project manager and contractor have assured you and I that the specifications of the elevator are a perfect fit for the shaft. I’m I right? (Custom-fit close).&lt;/i&gt; With yeses at every stage so far, you very casually remove your Parker pen from inside your coat pocket, open and turn the handle towards him with one hand and, with the other hand, the page with the dotted line and the bank funds transfer form, and say, &lt;i&gt;“Please sign here and here” (assumptive close).&lt;/i&gt; He signs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The waiter at the pub asks, &lt;i&gt;“Moto ama baridi?” (Warm or cold?).&lt;/i&gt; This is the alternative close. Notice how it does not matter what response you give- either way the sale happens. In the corporate world, &lt;i&gt;“Do you want to sign with the blue pen or the black one?” or “Would you like to pay by cheque or cash, Sir?” or “would you like us to meet at 8.30am Monday, or is the following day, Tuesday 10am better?&quot;&lt;/i&gt; Plenty other ways to close happen in our everyday lives. Look out and learn from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As this column has shown, what really makes closing difficult is the fear of rejection more than the tightening of the stomach at the moment of closing. And it’s just that: a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do buyers hesitate to buy at the time of closing yet are ripe for it? Because they are human. You and I aren’t any different. Now that you are equipped, give these techniques your best shot. The knot in your stomach won’t go away when you do; it’ll still be there. It never goes away no matter how fluent you are. However, repeatedly putting your best foot forward will tame it, and more importantly, get you to complete the sales process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    /* * * CONFIGURATION VARIABLES * * */
    var disqus_shortname = 'lendmeyourears';
    var disqus_identifier = '2015-04-15';
    
    /* * * DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE * * */
    (function() {
        var dsq = document.createElement('script'); dsq.type = 'text/javascript'; dsq.async = true;
        dsq.src = '//' + disqus_shortname + '.disqus.com/embed.js';
        (document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0] || document.getElementsByTagName('body')[0]).appendChild(dsq);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;!--
//&lt;![CDATA[
	twatchData = 'page='+encodeURIComponent( window.location );
	if( typeof document.referrer != 'undefined' &amp;&amp; document.referrer != '' ) {
		twatchData += '&amp;ref='+encodeURIComponent( document.referrer );
	}
	twatchData += '&amp;no_cookies=true';
	if( typeof screen.width != 'undefined' ) {
		twatchData += '&amp;resolution='+screen.width+'x'+screen.height;
	}
	document.write('&lt;scr'+'ipt type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; '+
	'src=&quot;http://www.lendmeyourears.co.ke/twatch/remote/js_logger.php?'+twatchData+'&quot;&gt;'+
	'&lt;/scr'+'ipt&gt;');
//]]&gt;
//--&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://lendmeyourears.co.ke/2015/04/15/learn-from-daily/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lendmeyourears.co.ke/2015/04/15/learn-from-daily/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Access to information is losing currency as the selling gambit</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;As long as access to information is lopsided to the seller’s advantage, buyer-beware will still trump. With information access being equal, seller-beware comes to the fore.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The terrorist attack in Garissa was followed globally as it was happening, yet newspaper sales are on the decline. How? Readers prefer other ways of consuming news, via the ubiquitous phone, internet and digital TV with its plethora of channels. Many media houses have an app or website. Some statistics put newspaper digital-media reach at a staggering 82% of online adult population in more mature economies. Singular access to information was the preserve of the traditional seller and so, selling was dependent on selectively exposing buyers to information. That was then, digital is now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Access to information is no longer the preserve of the seller and can no longer be his trump card. For instance, Googling will give you a plethora of information about the causes of pain in your lower back; joining a Facebook group of Lower-Back Pain sufferers or tweeting #LowerBackPain will give you an avalanche of first-hand insights on the condition; regularly tuning into a medical TV channel and downloading an app to measure and manage the pressure you are applying to your lower back will shed further light still. All this while, you have not gone to see the seller (doctor). When you ultimately do so, you are a walking encyclopedia on lower back pain. You are still a lay person, yes; only informed. The wise doctor will not handle a digital you as he would have your analogue version.  He is a second opinion; the internet was the first!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full impact of equal access to information has not come full circle into this market yet. However, with an explosion of youth and Kenya touted as an IT hub, the time is nigh. The progressive seller is wise enough to start evolving into this changing landscape. How? Finding other ways to connect with the buyer. Instead of the doctor feeling offended at being challenged by the patient based on his Google-found knowledge, the wise one will explore. “How do you feel about what you read?” The patient (buyer) may have the information, and possibly successfully self medicated in the past, but he is still not a medical doctor. What he needs is acknowledgment of his interest and more importantly guidance (educating) on the pros and cons of what he is proposing for him to see. Insisting that “I’m the doctor. Choose whether you will listen to me or Google&quot; may win you the argument but will lose you future sales. A (buyer) car enthusiast at a bazaar will not be won over by the seller excitedly sharing the features of the Subaru; the buyer most probably knows them much more than you do. But because you have superior product knowledge does not translate to superior selling abilities: you flip out your phone and invite the buyer to access information and you arrive at a (guided) solution together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In traditional selling, the examples shared were considered time-wasting. Not anymore.  Acknowledgment, education and discussion towards building trust and connection are the new trump-card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;b&gt;Sales Pitch mourns with the bereaved families of the terrorist attack in Garissa and condemns the cowardly act of the terrorists. Whatever product they are selling, the price they are levying does not justify it.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    /* * * CONFIGURATION VARIABLES * * */
    var disqus_shortname = 'lendmeyourears';
    var disqus_identifier = '2015-04-08';
    
    /* * * DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE * * */
    (function() {
        var dsq = document.createElement('script'); dsq.type = 'text/javascript'; dsq.async = true;
        dsq.src = '//' + disqus_shortname + '.disqus.com/embed.js';
        (document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0] || document.getElementsByTagName('body')[0]).appendChild(dsq);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;!--
//&lt;![CDATA[
	twatchData = 'page='+encodeURIComponent( window.location );
	if( typeof document.referrer != 'undefined' &amp;&amp; document.referrer != '' ) {
		twatchData += '&amp;ref='+encodeURIComponent( document.referrer );
	}
	twatchData += '&amp;no_cookies=true';
	if( typeof screen.width != 'undefined' ) {
		twatchData += '&amp;resolution='+screen.width+'x'+screen.height;
	}
	document.write('&lt;scr'+'ipt type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; '+
	'src=&quot;http://www.lendmeyourears.co.ke/twatch/remote/js_logger.php?'+twatchData+'&quot;&gt;'+
	'&lt;/scr'+'ipt&gt;');
//]]&gt;
//--&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://lendmeyourears.co.ke/2015/04/08/access-to-information/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lendmeyourears.co.ke/2015/04/08/access-to-information/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Think like a business owner for success in sales, and excel</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the challenges many salespeople face is the ability to think like a businessman.  In most instances they get by without having to but in some they struggle when they don’t. Sales representatives in oil companies and fast-moving-consumer-goods (FMCG) plus corporate and wealth managers in banks and investment firms are examples of sellers who find themselves in this dilemma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This happens because their buyers are businessmen and they are employees.  An employee’s thinking is as different from a businessman’s as day is from night. The employee works in a structured environment, with a regular income and his financial horizon is usually 30 days to the next salary; the businessman is intensely focused on the success of his business, a comparatively unstructured environment, erratic income and a long term financial horizon.  He is not a buyer you will ‘push’ a product to that does not make business sense to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, in addition to overseeing the supply of the contractual amount of fuel say 10,000 litres to the dealer (petrol station owner) the oil company’s reps job is to ‘push’ more sales with every depletion.  Phone calls, visits and emails insisting on this rarely help.   Understanding business, banks have Premier Business Clubs to as a platform for their businessmen clients to network and FMCGs have aggressive marketing campaigns ‘pulling’ customers to ask for their product much as the distributor has already bought them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The salesperson though must offer a ‘push’ with business sense. This starts with a genuine interest in the buyer’s business and therefore gaining his trust. I once read in Forbes that to be useful to an organization, find out what keeps the CEO (who is a businessman) awake at night and make it your business during the day. To succeed in selling, understand what the businessman wants from his business and make it your business to help him succeed. The typical employee response I get whenever I ask this question is, “it’s just money he wants”, as if to suggest the employee would work for free!  It could be he wants recognition or to plug an income leakage for his fleet of lorries.
Remember he’s depositing Ksh. 10M as security with your oil company was not for lack of an alternative avenue to invest it in. With genuine understanding, it becomes easier to help him succeed in achieving his goal and easier to present a business case to your employer (the other business you represent) why the delayed payment has occurred and how it will be settled in a win-win fashion. Bereft of such a case, credit control follows what the policy says, and the account is suspended or closed and your selling is impeded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The businessman’s frame-of-mind is solution-oriented. He wants to know how it can be done, not why it cannot. Company policy is therefore subject to interpretation for the progressive seller. This does not imply practising unethical practices. No. It implies not wearing blinders in the application of the policy and using policy as a guideline not deadline to protect your employer while growing and retaining business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The progressive representative therefore visits the dealer’s clients with him and even presents credible cases to him on how to increase traffic to his fuel station; thus he can justify to the dealer why he should replenish when he requests him to, because there is business sense to it. And the more the dealer replenishes, the more the oil company sells and the more the salesperson sells too.  And all because he thought and acted like a businessman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    /* * * CONFIGURATION VARIABLES * * */
    var disqus_shortname = 'lendmeyourears';
    var disqus_identifier = '2015-04-01';
    
    /* * * DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE * * */
    (function() {
        var dsq = document.createElement('script'); dsq.type = 'text/javascript'; dsq.async = true;
        dsq.src = '//' + disqus_shortname + '.disqus.com/embed.js';
        (document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0] || document.getElementsByTagName('body')[0]).appendChild(dsq);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;!--
//&lt;![CDATA[
	twatchData = 'page='+encodeURIComponent( window.location );
	if( typeof document.referrer != 'undefined' &amp;&amp; document.referrer != '' ) {
		twatchData += '&amp;ref='+encodeURIComponent( document.referrer );
	}
	twatchData += '&amp;no_cookies=true';
	if( typeof screen.width != 'undefined' ) {
		twatchData += '&amp;resolution='+screen.width+'x'+screen.height;
	}
	document.write('&lt;scr'+'ipt type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; '+
	'src=&quot;http://www.lendmeyourears.co.ke/twatch/remote/js_logger.php?'+twatchData+'&quot;&gt;'+
	'&lt;/scr'+'ipt&gt;');
//]]&gt;
//--&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://lendmeyourears.co.ke/2015/04/01/think-like-a/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lendmeyourears.co.ke/2015/04/01/think-like-a/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Two years on- 12 ways to get the buyer's ear and become a first-class seller</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today’s article is the 101st and marks this column’s 2nd anniversary; as with any milestone, reflection is advisable.  Only editorial space limits the depth to which we can reflect and so we’ll look at twelve ways in which we can connect with the buyer; which is the underlying theme of &lt;i&gt;Sales Pitch&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;1. “Third World is a state of the mind and until we change our attitude as Africans, if there is a fourth, fifth and even sixth world, we will be in it.” (PLO Lumumba ).&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; The seller’s attitude can spiral him into the sixth world of disconnection or raise him to the first where connection with the buyer is almost tangible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;2.  Quit hearing and start listening.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Actively listening acts as the rudder that steers you to the buyer’s soul. Research into live buyer interactions of 800 sellers proves this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;3.  Believing in your product produces emotional contagion, infecting the prospect and making him less adversarial and open to new possibilities.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;4. Love what you hate about selling.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Inviting the walk-in client who just wants a quote to a tour of the shop floor may just tilt the balance in your favour when he is making a decision on which quote to go with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;5. Be prepared. Always.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; The 5Rs help: 
	&lt;ul&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;R&lt;/b&gt;epresentation (how you present yourself),&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;R&lt;/b&gt;epertoire (your sales kit),&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;R&lt;/b&gt;esearch (your prospect),&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;R&lt;/b&gt;ehearsal (practice) and&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;R&lt;/b&gt;epetition (of the first four always, for one can never be too prepared).&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;6. How do you sell to someone whose budget at his local pub is the half a million shillings you can only access as a loan?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;First, get out of your way. Get rid of the smugness of self-righteousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;7. Connecting the dots happens when the seller paints a picture of how his product solves the buyer’s problem.&lt;/b&gt; &lt;br /&gt;The existence and contents of this column were unknown to the author two years ago, yet here we are 100 dots later. To connect one must connect the dots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;8. Educating the customer as a way to sell produces a powerful connection.&lt;/b&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Educating is genuinely seeking to create understanding about the client’s situation or your product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;9. Framing a sale in terms of experiential satisfaction as opposed to material possession is more likely to get the sale and repeat purchases.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Experience sells because we derive much more pleasure buying experiences than we do buying goods though it is the latter that attracts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;10. Brochures (like Power Pont slides) don’t connect with the buyer, salespeople do.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Prospects (and that includes you) hardly read marketing material or act on it little more than they get moved by the inanimate slide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;11. Fend off technical jargon when selling.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;i&gt;“Explain it to me like I’m a two year old”&lt;/i&gt; should not be seen as a condescending term for the salesperson. It should be the Holy Grail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;12. Let that moment of tension (when closing is imminent) galvanize you to ask for the cheque.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Many times the buyer wants you to. Don’t cave into the tension. Close. The razzmatazz of football is a delight to watch, but did you score?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second birthday is commonly referred to as &lt;i&gt;terrible twos&lt;/i&gt;. It needn’t be. These “connectors” will see you aiming for the terrific twelve.  Progressively build on one a month as we head for the 3rd birthday.  Why? Because the internet gives the buyer access to the same information as the seller making them almost equal.  A seismic shift in selling is thus necessary, for the snowballing tsunami of 'seller beware' is about to hit shore.&lt;p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    /* * * CONFIGURATION VARIABLES * * */
    var disqus_shortname = 'lendmeyourears';
    var disqus_identifier = '2015-03-25';
    
    /* * * DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE * * */
    (function() {
        var dsq = document.createElement('script'); dsq.type = 'text/javascript'; dsq.async = true;
        dsq.src = '//' + disqus_shortname + '.disqus.com/embed.js';
        (document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0] || document.getElementsByTagName('body')[0]).appendChild(dsq);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;!--
//&lt;![CDATA[
    twatchData = 'page='+encodeURIComponent( window.location );
    if( typeof document.referrer != 'undefined' &amp;&amp; document.referrer != '' ) {
        twatchData += '&amp;ref='+encodeURIComponent( document.referrer );
    }
    twatchData += '&amp;no_cookies=true';
    if( typeof screen.width != 'undefined' ) {
        twatchData += '&amp;resolution='+screen.width+'x'+screen.height;
    }
    document.write('&lt;scr'+'ipt type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; '+
    'src=&quot;http://www.lendmeyourears.co.ke/twatch/remote/js_logger.php?'+twatchData+'&quot;&gt;'+
    '&lt;/scr'+'ipt&gt;');
//]]&gt;
//--&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://lendmeyourears.co.ke/2015/03/25/two-years-on/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lendmeyourears.co.ke/2015/03/25/two-years-on/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Avoid using the word 'convenient' while selling</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;Avoid using the word 'convenient' when selling. Let it come from the buyer. Strive instead to get the buyer to vividly visualize how your product solves his problem. The word 'convenient' when selling is anything but.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the word 'convenient' when selling could be losing you sales. First, the definition, which the dictionary gives as, &lt;i&gt;“fitting in well with a person's needs, activities, and plans&quot;&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And therein lays the problem. Every person or organization may have similar universal but wildly different individual needs, activities and plans. To therefore say your product offers convenience (and all products claim to) is not useful to the buyer because he does not see how from his point of view. For example, with millions of Kenyans on Mpesa which is “convenient”, millions others still aren’t because they haven’t had their aha! moment. Average sellers who use only the word convenient to show how their product benefits the buyer, work under the assumption that “the buyer knows his problems, will see how my product/service can resolve it, and will therefore buy”. In truth, he doesn’t see, nor buy. Instead of telling the buyer how convenient your service is, and leave it at that, help him visualize by connecting the dots for him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Borrowing from last week’s example, a through-way elevator (one that opens from opposite sides) fits well into an airport’s needs, activities and plans because it eases traffic flow and therefore queues by allowing passengers to alight from either side of it; that’s how convenience shows for the airport. Same product, in a hospital, saves lives because it cuts down by half the time it takes in an emergency to wheel a patent from casualty to theatre and because entry and exist is possible without turning the stretcher-that’s how it fits into the hospital administrator’s needs, activities and plans; the convenience to a warehouse manager is the time saved and heightened safety as the forklift’s movement across the floor are limited and there’s no ramp to climb.  That’s how it fits into the warehouse managers needs, activities and plans. Looking at these three scenarios, one begins to see why a plain, “our two-door lift will offer you convenience” lacks descriptive usefulness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even dictionaries give an example of the usage of a word after defining it. Not spelling out how your product dovetails with the buyers pain, forces him to do so himself which is not a priority as he has other pressing problems- like meeting his targets. And even if he were to do so, it’s a strain because he does not know how your product works and may therefore create the wrong connections in his mind, which will hamper your sales efforts. In addition, the seller who plainly uses the word convenient, loses a golden opportunity to emotionally connect with the buyer by showing him that he understands his business and feels his pain. It is this connection that lends itself to an easier close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word convenient is not entirely misplaced in the selling process though. In fact, it's music to the seller’s ear when, after connecting the dots for the buyer, a bulb lights up in the buyer’s head and he says, “Wow! That’s convenient”, like I did when my aha! moment at M-Pesa’s convenience sunk in. Then you know you are on the same page-  your prognosis and diagnosis of his problem are correct and complete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    /* * * CONFIGURATION VARIABLES * * */
    var disqus_shortname = 'lendmeyourears';
    var disqus_identifier = '2015-03-18';
    
    /* * * DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE * * */
    (function() {
        var dsq = document.createElement('script'); dsq.type = 'text/javascript'; dsq.async = true;
        dsq.src = '//' + disqus_shortname + '.disqus.com/embed.js';
        (document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0] || document.getElementsByTagName('body')[0]).appendChild(dsq);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;!--
//&lt;![CDATA[
	twatchData = 'page='+encodeURIComponent( window.location );
	if( typeof document.referrer != 'undefined' &amp;&amp; document.referrer != '' ) {
		twatchData += '&amp;ref='+encodeURIComponent( document.referrer );
	}
	twatchData += '&amp;no_cookies=true';
	if( typeof screen.width != 'undefined' ) {
		twatchData += '&amp;resolution='+screen.width+'x'+screen.height;
	}
	document.write('&lt;scr'+'ipt type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; '+
	'src=&quot;http://www.lendmeyourears.co.ke/twatch/remote/js_logger.php?'+twatchData+'&quot;&gt;'+
	'&lt;/scr'+'ipt&gt;');
//]]&gt;
//--&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://lendmeyourears.co.ke/2015/03/18/avoid-using-the-word/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lendmeyourears.co.ke/2015/03/18/avoid-using-the-word/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Stretch the buyer's pain to help them see the need to buy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the counter terrorism hit series &lt;i&gt;24&lt;/i&gt;, protagonist Jack Bauer uses pain to acquire information. When a villain has a wound, Jack pierces, twists and inflicts further pain until it sears right through the terrorist’s body. Nothing focuses the mind with the precision with which pain does. The natural reaction to pain is to avoid it and the average seller does this in an attempt to be nice. Progressive sellers on the other hand have no qualms stretching the buyer’s pain; they make him vividly visualise his pain by painting a picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say I’m selling elevators and specifically want a hospital to buy a two door one (also known as through way as it opens from either side). The statement, “it will allow staff to exit the lift without having to turn the stretcher” is bland; “in the event of an emergency, your staff will save time as they will not have to turn the stretcher to exit or enter the lift”, is much better as it zeros in on a pain spot for the hospital- emergencies; yet still it can be improved to, “based on the design of the hospital, and our observations, in a life-threatening situation, it takes an average of eleven minutes to wheel a patient from the casualty on the ground floor to the theatre on the back side on left wing of the first floor. Time is of the essence when saving a life and the hallmark your hospital is its ability to save lives. Reducing eleven minutes to four, could be the difference between saving a life-or not. From our statistics, you have seven emergency cases every day, and as such the opportunity to lose a life is compounded seven-fold every day because of the time it takes to wheel a patient whose life is in your hands from casualty to theatre. Loss of life is irreversible; more so when it happens in a hospital and when one feels they could have done something to prevent it. How has your experience been?” Stretching the pain until the buyer contributes to the episode by way of an example or squirming in his seat has him at his most receptive moment to open up to installing your through way lift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When he agrees that a problem exists requiring an emergency solution, you ask the billion shilling leading question: “How would you like it to be?” The response lends itself to allowing you show how your through way elevator will save lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To effectively stretch the pain, the seller must have done his research into the specific pain in question. Notice how detailed the third response is. It follows therefore that the pain in a hospital is not the pain at an airport though the product is the same. For instance, the pain for an airport is the unending queues of persons who enter and exit the same lift door to go to different wings of the same floor. Long queues means irritated travellers; long queues means pulling staff off their roles to assist thus lowering productivity, sales and therefore profits; irritated travellers means screaming children, agitated adults tweeting and posting their frustration on Facebook and Instagram about your s-l-o-w airport and a global destination enjoying global negative publicity . &lt;i&gt;Stretching the pain is not lying; it is painting a true picture of how things are or how they can be if not addressed and is driven by a genuine desire to want to help.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
    /* * * CONFIGURATION VARIABLES * * */
    var disqus_shortname = 'lendmeyourears';
    var disqus_identifier = '2015-03-11';
    
    /* * * DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE * * */
    (function() {
        var dsq = document.createElement('script'); dsq.type = 'text/javascript'; dsq.async = true;
        dsq.src = '//' + disqus_shortname + '.disqus.com/embed.js';
        (document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0] || document.getElementsByTagName('body')[0]).appendChild(dsq);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;!--
//&lt;![CDATA[
	twatchData = 'page='+encodeURIComponent( window.location );
	if( typeof document.referrer != 'undefined' &amp;&amp; document.referrer != '' ) {
		twatchData += '&amp;ref='+encodeURIComponent( document.referrer );
	}
	twatchData += '&amp;no_cookies=true';
	if( typeof screen.width != 'undefined' ) {
		twatchData += '&amp;resolution='+screen.width+'x'+screen.height;
	}
	document.write('&lt;scr'+'ipt type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; '+
	'src=&quot;http://www.lendmeyourears.co.ke/twatch/remote/js_logger.php?'+twatchData+'&quot;&gt;'+
	'&lt;/scr'+'ipt&gt;');
//]]&gt;
//--&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://lendmeyourears.co.ke/2015/03/11/stretch-the-buyers/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lendmeyourears.co.ke/2015/03/11/stretch-the-buyers/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
